Women's Ephemera Collection
Women's Ephemera Collection
1970-1988
1.25 linear ft.
Material relating to Equal Rights Ammendment and other women's issues, chiefly from New York state with some material from Florida.
3174735
Biographical History
New York has seen several notable events in the history of women's rights, most notably the Seneca Falls Convention on women's rights held in July 1848, hosted by Lucretia Mott, Mary Ann M'Clintock and Elizabeth Cady Stanton.
The National Organization for Women (NOW) was founded in 1966 by Betty Friedan and Pauli Murray in an effort to confront with concrete action the issues of political, professional, and social inequality between the sexes. As early as its second conference in 1967, NOW adopts the passage of the Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) and repeal of all abortion laws, becoming the first national organization to support the legalization of abortion. NOW intensely campaigned for passage of the ERA, which was approved in the House of Representatives and the Senate and submitted to state legislatures for ratification in 1972. The organization has 550 chapters in all 50 U.S. states and Washington D.C.
The Coordinating Committee of Women in the Historical Profession (CCWHP) was formed in 1969 in response to the exclusion and sexism rampant in the American Historical Association (AHA). The goals of the organization included recruiting more women into the profession, alleviate discrimination, and encourage the study and teaching of women's history. The CCWHP quickly became affiliated with the AHA and in 1974 the Conference Group on Women's History (CGWH) was formed. In 1955 the CCWHP and CGWH were combined to form the Council for Women in History (CCWH), which it is known by today.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Women's Ephemera Collection consists of material relating to women's issues, chiefly in New York State with some material related to Florida.
Correspondence-subject files consists mainly of correspondence and newsletters.
Printed material consists of clippings.
Writings consists of essays, bibliographies, and other similar material.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence-subject files are arranged first alphabetically by sender, then chronologically, with unidentified or undated material at the end. Printed material is arranged chronologically with undated material at the end. Writings are arranged alphabetically by last name with unidentified material at the end.
Related Material
The has a plethora of information related to women's rights. Please for more material.
Subject and Genre Headings
Activism and social reform; New York State; Women Authors; National Organization for Women.; Women -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Women -- Political activity.; Equal rights amendments -- United States.; Feminists -- United States.; Women's rights.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Newsletters.; Manuscripts for publication.; Bibliographies.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Unspecified, 1989.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Cayuga County Community College, 1979; undated (Box 1)
  - Coordinating Committee on Women in the Historical Profession
    - CCWHP newsletter, 1979-1983 (Box 1)
    - CCWHP CGWH newsletter, 1979-1981 (Box 1)
    - CGWH newsletter, 1980-1984 (Box 1)
  - Elizabeth Cady Stanton Foundation, 1980-1986; undated (Box 1)
  - Florida Women's Political Caucus, 1971-1975; undated (Box 1)
  - Journalism and Women Symposium, JAWS newsletter, 1987 (Box 1)
  - National Organization for Women (NOW)
    - Do It NOW, 1971-1973, 1977; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - National NOW Times, 1977-1981; 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Organizational information (Box 1)
  - National Organization for Women (NOW), Florida
    - Correspondence, 1973-1980; undated (Box 1)
    - Newsletters, 1976; 1 item (Box 1)
  - National Organization for Women (NOW), New York
    - Central New York NOW Times, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1980; undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - New York State newsletter, 1980 (Box 2)
    - News Greater Syracuse Chapter, 1980 (Box 2)
  - New York State History Network newsletter, 1979-1984 (Box 2)
  - Planned Parenthood, 1973-1981 (Box 2)
  - Project on the Status and Education of Women, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
  - Society of American Archivists Women's Caucus, 1980-1986 (Box 2)
  - Steinem, Gloria, undated (Box 2)
  - Upstate New York Women's History Conference, 1971-1988; undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Women and the Arts Conference, 1979; undated (Box 2)
  - Women's Division of the State of New York newsletter, 1979-1981 (Box 2)
  - Women's Information Center, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - A-Y miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 2)
- Printed material
  - Clippings, 1971-1987; undated; includes article by Germaine Greer; 4 folders (Box 3)
- Writings
  - Miscellaneous, 1976-1982; undated (Box 3)